[SPEAKER_01]: I had a few questions sent to me, and they all seem to be about rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is rūpa?
[SPEAKER_01]: Give me information about rūpa, so that I can understand it, so that I can be
[SPEAKER_01]: You can always answer someone, you know, you can give them the definition, the dictionary definition, rūpa, such and such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can give them the English word, matter, form, resistance, and that will all be on the level of, you know, abstract information, and will make no difference in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't, it doesn't apply to the place where it should apply.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really, it's like, how do you... how should you regard the phenomenon of rūpa that is in your experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is rūpa in your experience?
[SPEAKER_02]: Practically speaking, what is the first rūpa?
[SPEAKER_02]: Pretty much the framework of all other rūpa as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is no other rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, understanding rūpa on any other level, will be misunderstanding it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, understand rūpa on the level of the body, you understood all rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: You escaped the rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rūpa won't find a footing in this experience anymore, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the body and...
[SPEAKER_01]: But you cannot experience the body
[SPEAKER_01]: Without perceiving it, I can't experience, I can't perceive the body, this...
[SPEAKER_02]: Without that rūpa being there, already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can't just experience body without perceiving it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: The experience of the body is perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I can't just body
[SPEAKER_02]: Without any... without the aggregator perception, without... well, without other aggregates, it's always the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practically speaking, then, understanding of the... the rūpa, the only rūpa that you have, the only rūpa through which you can experience other rūpa, the... the... your body, the rūpa of your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practically speaking, how would you... how would you understand that?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is there to be understood?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, is it physical examination of your form, for which you're basically just observing it with your senses?
[SPEAKER_02]: That would not be on the level of understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be on the level of, you know, collecting random information about the properties of that form, externally, through observation.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: What we're talking about is understanding your body internally.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, understanding the relationship
[SPEAKER_02]: That you have, internally, with a, like, facticity, the presence of your body for what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the mind that's paired with the body needs to understand it on the level of that pairing, not on the level of the external appearance and observation and sensations and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that is secondary to that primordial form, primordial rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you understand the meaning?
[SPEAKER_02]: Ownership doesn't have... it doesn't have infinite amount of possibilities or pathways.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always going to go down either ownership or non-ownership, taking it permanently, as permanent when it's not permanent, taking it as mine when it's not mine, taking it as pleasurable when it's not pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what needs to be understood on that fundamental level, on that internal
[SPEAKER_02]: You being paired... You being paired with the body, but even thought of me and I am, implies the image of that body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's all within.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it... you can't... that's why you can't separate the rūpa, examine it individually from other aggregates, or... or kind of access it with other aggregates, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's within those aggregates, just remove the ignorance in regard to certain properties of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it same applies what I said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Non-ownership, non-delight, not seeing it as pleasurable, seeing it as dangerous, seeing it as not worth delighting in.
[SPEAKER_02]: That applies to the body, applies to the feelings, applies to the perception, applies to the intention, applies to the consciousness, applies to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those universal recognitions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you just practice in regard to the body, those recognitions, you are practicing in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're practicing in regard to the five aggregates, you're practicing in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: But practically speaking, even the thought of five aggregates, you know, it's more often than not, it's abstract to people.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, the five aggregates, okay, one, two, my perception, my... No, it's the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the experience here and now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before I start thinking about the five aggregates, that's already what five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Self-awareness of this moment here and now that endures, it's already what the five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Affected with upādāna and assumptions and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: A lack of clarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why mindfulness of the body developed to the extent necessary for the final knowledge will uproot all of the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what mindfulness of the body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sustaining, composing rightly that framework on the right level, on that internal recognition of the framework
[SPEAKER_02]: Stuff with my body, on the body, within the body, for as long as it takes until I get the magical recognition of some, you know, divine truth of liberation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the body on the right...
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the body on the right level, recognizing it as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I said before, like, seeing the body as peripherally already enduring there, before you start looking at it directly, that's the level that all these understandings need to apply.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before you start thinking about the body, the reason you can start thinking about the body, because it's already there, peripherally, enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to start seeing that, without needing to look at and make it forward, make it something you need to stare at, in order for it to exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by seeing that, you automatically start seeing this... this kind of disconnect?
[SPEAKER_01]: Between...
[SPEAKER_01]: Between you...
[SPEAKER_01]: And the body, there's this... there is a separation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, that separation is kind of gratuitously generated through mistaking what the actual body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you see the body and the aggregates on the level of that peripheral, everything is within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is no more disconnect.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the Buddha was describing, he says, it doesn't matter, like, whatever form there is, past, future, present, big, small, personal, impersonal, delightful, ugly,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he knows it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter how it feels.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter how it's perceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: What matters is knowing the framework that forms present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not about going into...
[SPEAKER_02]: The details, the specifics.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about observing it directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's... that's what the body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what rūpa is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rūpa is recognizing body on that peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_01]: We always talk about the elements, you know, it's made up of elements.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, well, you can you can now extend that peripheral context.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that body that you see peripherally, you can now start seeing it as solidity, fluidity, airy, fiery, space, all of that, on the peripheral level, not on the level of your focusing meditation objects, on which you can't even see this mere body.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't observe directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only think you're observing it through watching some random secondary sensations of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now I have a clear context of the body, mindful of the body in that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: On a peripheral level, as a necessary basis for you and I sitting here together, talking, discussing this mindfully, in the present moment, while the knowledge of the body being there behind this, as a framework to this, endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, as I do that,
And then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's next?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think what's next?
[SPEAKER_01]: I see that it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I mean, what's next?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you need to do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: You described, okay, I'm mindful of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's next then?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And putting from mindfulness to the body, is that enough?
[SPEAKER_02]: But what else do you need to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I need to... Well, if I read in the suttas, I need to recognize certain qualities of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by protecting the mindfulness that you already developed...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, you need to protect it for a longer time, until you see what needs to be seen within it, for which you already have information.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's anicca.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can tell it, oh, this is anicca, but until you recognize that anicca, in that which you now have, which you protect on the right level, it won't be anicca that you're seeing, until you recognize it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will be just that
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's the important part to recognize, like, okay, so now I need to do something else, and then people forget that whatever else you need to do, which, yes, there is factually things you need to do, but none of those things should be done at the expense of mindfulness of the body on that peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that must remain unchanged.
[SPEAKER_02]: You must protect that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, doing of these other things must be within that, not in
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your priority.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the framework.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the solution is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, you need to, like, develop it further within that, not instead of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in place of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, okay, now I'll remove this, because I did it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me do the next thing, because that's completed.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's one within that, within that, within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words,
[SPEAKER_02]: All you need to do is practice mindfulness to the extent... mindfulness of the body to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you see the body correctly, on that peripheral level, you don't need to do anything, on the level of doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's the problem here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the pull, the pressure to do something, at the expense of which you end up not doing what you know... what you're already doing rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kind
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you have mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically playing the string instrument.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's too tight, too loose, there will be a horrible sound.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you get the right amount of tension, then the sound's perfect.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, being mindful of the body, on the level of that peripheral correctly, sustaining that, is what that right amount of tension is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the more you sustain it, the more samādhi you will have.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, of course, the natural tendency is to kind of, you know, either slack it or tighten it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The natural tendency is to fall from that middle way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if person doesn't recognize
[SPEAKER_02]: the middle way for what it is, as something that they must protect and stay with, then they will, almost out of a sense of duty for practice, go on and start doing things that will compromise that right amount of tension.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they'll become too tense, so they will fall from the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or they'll become too loose, so they'll fall from the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why you can't have too much of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can have too much of pondering about properties of things and nature of things and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Too much of not pondering, too much of just being, you know, composed, but you can't have too much of just recognizing the right context, the right framework.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, what do you do next when you developed recognition of the body, of rūpa, of form, on that peripheral level, as something that endures there, that doesn't belong to you, but it's a necessary basis for the entire world you're experiencing here and now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, probably first thing you do is not
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't sort of neglect it, don't ignore it, and don't try to speed it up, so to speak, but actually allow it to endure and try to become more and more familiar
[SPEAKER_02]: And you immediately recognize the tune, the right... the right amount of tension for the perfect music.
[SPEAKER_02]: And how do you then protect that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Virtue, sense restraint, guarding the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have too much of virtue.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if you're doubtful about everything else... Oh, anicca, what is anicca?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you do?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you address that?
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the answers to all these questions?
[SPEAKER_02]: But teach samupādā, five aggregates, consciousness, infinite consciousness states... All of that is your own mind trying to throw you from that right amount of tension that's based on the right recognition of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the music starts to flow, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, no doubt, the mind will be coming up with his thoughts and doubts.
[SPEAKER_02]: You recognize, okay, so that's something that I must include within that peripheral cognition of the body that's enduring there, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not put that doubt first, and then trying to solve this peripheral cognition of the body that's enduring there, that I already
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever perceiving arises, whatever perception arises, he sees it in relation, it is dependently arisen to.
[SPEAKER_01]: On what?
[SPEAKER_01]: On this body.
[SPEAKER_02]: On the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he still, he doesn't, he refuses to put that first, and that peripheral condition of the body second.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: He keeps the peripheral condition of the body first, and whatever else arises, it's second.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever else arises, he feels, he perceives, he intends detached from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just keep doing that until all the passion is gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: How long that would be?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Half a day, one day, seven days, seven weeks, seven months, seven years, as satipaṭṭhāna says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, so you're keeping that context, mindfulness of the body, and whatever is arising in your experience, you see it in relation
[SPEAKER_02]: So, sooner or later, you have to recognize that, if you want to practice rightly, and then refrain from putting those questions first,
[SPEAKER_02]: And everything else second to it, until you find the answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, fundamentally, you end up acting out of pressure, as we said so many times.
[SPEAKER_02]: But instead, the pressuring questions, the pressuring doubts, and so on, what next, and whatever else your mind might be throwing at you, you put that second to that peripherally recognized mindfulness of the body that's enduring there, and endure it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Endure the pressure a second and don't let your mind, don't allow yourself, don't choose it first and then start acting out of which will put your recognition of the body as peripheral thing enduring there second or even disappear.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will lose mindfulness in other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just back to that level of
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, when he feels a feeling, eh... the patujana, the ordinary person who doesn't have mindfulness, he feels a feeling, he feels connected to it, he doesn't see that, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he doesn't see the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can only go so far.
[SPEAKER_01]: As far as the body goes, that's as far as the feeling will go.
[SPEAKER_01]: For him, feeling goes, as you said... Infinite.
[SPEAKER_02]: Infinite.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he doesn't see the extent of it, yeah?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the infinite joy in the prospect of sensuality and the infinite dread in the prospect of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because puthujjana, untrained mind, does not recognize the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Does not see what the right tune is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It does not see it as a reason upon that peripherally enduring body that's there, because he doesn't see the peripherally enduring body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all he sees is just my feeling, whatever, whatever that feeling might be.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has no boundary, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when he feels a feeling, he feels it detached, when he has mindfulness of the body, for example, he knows that this feeling terminates at the body, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, he sees that, oh, the presence of the body has the presence of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: The presence of that peripheral body is the framework for this feeling, and the feeling cannot surpass that framework.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that framework is seen as something doesn't belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, anything dependent upon the framework can equally not belong to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever he feels, perceives, intends, it will be so detached.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will not be his, cannot be his, because he unplugged it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He unplugged the framework that was giving power to these things as his.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, this is a...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the ordinary person, we spoke about it last night, the
[SPEAKER_01]: When he feels pleasure, in hindsight, it goes so fast.
[SPEAKER_01]: Time flies by when you're having fun.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you're in pain, it drags.
[SPEAKER_01]: It goes very slow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very slow.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then for a person, because he is connected with that vast, infinite, boundless feeling of pain, boundless, infinite pleasure,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it will even out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because you're not resisting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know, the thing don't last... things don't last long enough when you want more of them right from the start.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you crave for more of them, then things are just too quick.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things last too long when you don't want them.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're dragging when you don't want even a second of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then every second feels like an hour.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, if you remove that attitude of delighting in pleasure and resisting the pain, then things just last for as long as they last.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is neither long nor short.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just for what they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that subjective side of time, in regard to things that are being felt, yeah, for somebody who is detached from feelings, that evens out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't matter if it's pain or pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: It does not imply, oh, like, you know, when will this end?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Asking that question, when will this pain end?
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't wait for it to end, means, oh, you already want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're not resisting it in the beginning, nor in the middle, nor in the end.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't matter how long it lasts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means you won't last longer than you would otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that it's not infinite.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you don't fall from recognizing the framework of that peripheral enduring body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you can see that its infinity is within the peripheral enduring body, which is not yours, and it's going to cease at some point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the infinity will cease at some point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, you can see this here, the body here, dying or falling apart, getting older.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, all those are like reflections that can help, but the point is to start seeing the body peripherally.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what the right mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not to look at it, oh, look, yes, I am aging,
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I'm falling apart, I'm ill, all these sensations, all of that is specific.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to see the nature of it already enduring there, because of which I can choose to look at the specific things in details.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that nature is already known.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if I ask you, do you have the body?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, tap into that knowledge that's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Learn how to see it with the corner of your eye, without needing to make it a subject, an object of your delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will be able to do that more accurately, more likely, let's say, like that, only if your physical behavior has been restrained, purified and maintained in virtue.
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole domain of that peripheral recognition with a corner of your eye does not exist for somebody who is still acting out of sensuality, does not even keep the precepts, is not moderate, does not watch their speech,
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's covered up with a pollution from your behavior.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if the behavior is unpolluted now, and somebody keeps telling you to discern it with a corner of your eye, peripherally, without looking at it directly, you will be able to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sooner or later, you're going to start seeing what that means.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a space for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you are uncluttering it, and then you recognize it.